Never forget why you are the church.
Turn your Bibles to Romans chapter 9.
We're going to continue right along in this chapter.
I want to go ahead and warn you this morning.
There's going to be a lot of scripture this morning, okay?
We're gonna go to the Old Testament a whole lot in Genesis.
We have to.
There's no way to go through Romans 9 without understanding
what the Jewish audience would understand because they had studied it from a child.
So we're going to be all over the place.
I have about 243,000 slides this morning, just kidding, just 52.
But either way, it was 71.
I did narrow it down a little bit this morning, but I do want you to know that sometimes I know that,
and I'm not apologizing for being teach you, a preacher, or whatever.
But listen, sometimes when you get into
the word and you get deep, you just got to get there.
Amen?
And so this morning, we're just going to have to get there, all right?
But remember, the audience Paul is writing to in particular here.
In chapters 9 through 11, he is answering
some important questions that the Jewish people and believers had about Jesus and the gospel.
The one here in chapter 9 is answering why not all Jews have accepted Jesus.
Obviously, this could be an issue for the Jewish person.
They believed in not simply a personal deliverance, but a national deliverance.
So if the majority of Israelites rejected Christ, how could he have been the true Messiah?
Now, how do we know that most rejected?
How do we know that that is the insinuation here?
Well, that's where we were last week in Romans chapter 9, verse one through 5 you're there, say read.
It says, Paul says, I say the truth in Christ, I lie not.
My conscience also bearing me witness in the Holy
Ghost, that I have great heaviness and continual sorrow in my heart.
For I wish that myself were accursed from Christ for my brethren.
My kinsmen according to the flesh, who are Israelites,
to whom pertaineth the adoption, and the glory,
and the covenants, and the giving of the law, and the
service of God, and the promises, whose are the
fathers, and of whom, as concerning the flesh, Christ came, who is overall God blessed forever.
Amen.
See, Paul sorrowed over the fact that
even though Israel was so spiritually privileged, they still rejected Christ.
By the way, he was praying in such a way or writing in
such a way that he said, I wish myself accursed.
That means I wish myself separated eternally from Christ, just so my brethren.
Just so my people, my family, could know Jesus.
You know, I know last week, we had a lot of people that were reminded about the reality of lostness in our families,
in our workplaces, in our communities and neighborhoods.
I want you to know something.
I am convicted by the conviction of Paul.
He loves the lost people and his people so much that he would literally write in my opinion.
I don't know if I could ever write this myself.
I wish to be accursed.
for their sake.
Guys, let us not get used to people around us being lost.
Amen?
But this morning, we continue to examine why this is.
And so why would so many Israelites reject Jesus?
Let's look at Romans chapter 9, verses 6 through 13.
It says this.
Not as though the word of God had taken an effect.
For they are not all Israel, which are of Israel.
Neither because they are the seed of Abraham, are they all children, but in Isaac, shall thy seed be called.
That is, they which are the children of the flesh.
These are not the children of God, but the children of the promise, are counted for the seed.
For this is the word of promise, that this time will I come, and Sarah shall have a son.
And not only this, but when Rebecca also had conceived
by one, even by our father Isaac, for the children being
not yet born, neither having done any good or
evil, that the purpose of God, according to election, might stand, not of works, but of him that calleth.
It was said unto her, the elder shall serve the younger.
As it is written, Jacob, have I loved, but Esau, have I hated.
I know for a fact that most of you right now are thinking, hmm,
how are you going to get through this preacher?
And we just going to get there.
Amen?
That's how we're going to get there.
We're going to continue with number one, the people of mercy.
Let's pray.
Father, I thank you for your word.
God, I thank you for clarity.
But God, I also thank you that God, we don't understand everything.
And we just have to trust you.
So, Lord, as Peter said in his writings in 2nd Peter, some
things that Paul writes are just hard to understand.
So God, give us a willing heart, a humble heart to receive.
God, allow me to preach this with clarity and liberty and power, God.
so that it can apply to our hearts as well.
And God we thank you.
God, I pray someone, if someone's here and they're thinking, well, how do
I become the elect, God, I pray that through your drawing of the Holy Spirit, God, they realize, they just get saved.
So God, I pray you draw.
We thank you, we love you, in Jesus name, pray.
Amen.
We'll continue in this 1st point of emphasis, the people of mercy,
but it'll also go right into our 2nd one as well this morning.
Paul just told the reality that most of his fellow Israelites have rejected Christ.
This was a troubling reality for everyone involved.
So much so that he had to clear up something immediately right out the gate in verse six.
He says, not as though the word of God had taken none effect.
In other words, God had made a promise to the people of Israel.
And he's telling them, hey, it's not that the word of God had failed.
So he explains it and we have to look at the Old Testament to really understand what the audience would understand.
So when God made a promise to Israel.
In Genesis 10, we get the genealogy from Noah with his 3 sons, Shemham, and Japheth.
In Genesis 11, right off of God scattering the
people of the earth with different languages,
from the Tower of Babel, we get a more specific genealogy of
Shem that leads all the way down to Terah, the father of Abram, Nahor, and Haran.
Now, this leads to a focus on Abram in particular.
This is when we get the first promise to Abraham,
in Genesis chapter 12, verse one and 3, it says this.
Now the Lord has said in Abram, get thee
out of thy country and from thy kindred, and from
thy father's house into a land that I will show thee, and
I'll make of thee a great nation, I'll bless thee and make thy name great, and thou shalt be a blessing.
And I'll bless them that bless thee and curse him that curseth thee,
and in thee shall all families of the earth, be blessed.
Now, the question is this that we have to ask, why did God choose Abram?
Let's think about that for a second.
There is no indication in scripture that Abram was seeking God.
As a matter of fact, his homeland was
or that really just means the land of the Chaldees.
This was what is known as the fertile crescent.
It was a land of great wealth and prosperity, but also of great idolatry and paganism.
They devoutly worship the false gods,
the moon, the stars, the planets, the sun, you'll
recognize the Chaldeans, as the people who ruled Babylon for some time.
It was a pagan society.
And that's where Abram was from.
Why is this so important?
Well, God chose Abram based on nothing but his choosing.
Abram did not earn this opportunity.
God called him.
Now, this shows the unconditional nature of this,
God shows the unconditional nature of this covenant through a covenantal ceremony in Genesis 15, verses 5 through 10.
It says this.
And he brought him forth abroad and said, look now toward
heaven and tell the stars that thou'll be able to number them, and he said unto him, so shall thy seed be.
And he believed in the Lord.
And he counted it to him for righteousness.
And he said unto him, I am the Lord that brought thee out of the Chaldees, to give thee this land to inherit it.
And he said, Lord God, whereby shall I know that I shall inherit it?
And he said unto him, take me a heifer of 3 years old
and a she goat of 3 years old and a ram of 3 years old and a turtle dove and a young pigeon.
And he took unto them all these things and divided them in the midst
and laid each piece, one against another, but the birds divided he not.
In other words, there was a ceremony attached to this covenant.
Now we're going to fast forward to Genesis 17.
Are y'all with me this morning so far?
Genesis 17, one through 8, we get another reminding,
another instance where his covenants brought up.
And when Abram was 90 years old and nine, 99 years old.
The Lord appeared to Abram and said unto him, I am the almighty God.
Walk before me and be thou perfect.
And I will make my covenant between me and thee and will multiply thee exceedingly.
And Abram fell on his face, and God talked to
him, saying, ask me, behold, my covenant is with thee, and thou shalt be a father of many nations,
neither shall thy name be anymore be called Abram, but
thy name shall be called Abraham, for a father of many nations have I made thee.
And I'll make the exceeding fruit, for when I'll make thee, make
nations of thee, and king shall come out of thee.
And I will establish my covenant between me and thee and thy seed
after thee and their generations for an everlasting covenant.
Everyone say everlasting.
To be a god unto thee and to thy seed after thee.
And I will give unto thee and to thy seed, after thee, the land wherein thou art a stranger.
All the land of Canaan for an everlasting possession.
Everyone say everlasting.
And I will be their God.
As a matter of fact, in the same chapter of 17, he establishes
a physical covenantal sign through circumcision.
Now, I gave you a whole lot just then.
I just spit it out at you, and I understand that.
But I want you to notice if you ever go back and jot
down on notes or whatever to read, reread that for yourself.
You'll realize this.
In all of these encounters, God appeared to Abraham.
Why is that important?
Because it was God who made the covenant, and it was God who would keep the covenant.
And this, according, Genesis 17, 7 is, again, an everlasting covenant.
What does that mean?
It doesn't end.
So now, once again, look at the reality, since we have
that backdrop, by the way, a Jewish person would know that by heart.
They would not have to be read that.
They would have studied that.
Honestly, they would have memorized that because that's what their culture was.
By the way, we need to get back to a culture of teaching our children God's word.
I mean, listen, I understand it's difficult.
I'm a dad, too.
I had the schedules and the things and all the stuff.
I get tired as well, but so often what we do is
we pawn our kids off to their to their life group leader.
We pawn our kids off to the children worker, and we say, well,
if they don't know, well, we brought you to church.
Why did the church do their job?
That's not the church's job.
Now, I have you know, we have some of the best children teachers in
the world right here at Cedar Grove Baptist Church.
My kids know the Bible because not just because of me and Heather,
but because of the teachers that have poured into them.
Listen, I can have some serious, some mature conversations about the Lord with my five-year-old.
Why?
Because she's been poured into.
You say, well, she's five.
She hasn't experienced anything.
When she does begin to experience this world, guess
what she'll be reminded of what she's been taught.
Are y'all with me, that was free.
That was not even in my 14 page of notes, you know what I'm saying?
But listen, let's look back at the reality that Paul brings up in Romans 9.
I say the truth in Christ.
I lie not, my conscience also bearing me witness in the Holy Ghost,
that I have great heaviness and continual sorrow in my heart.
For I wish that myself were a curse from Christ, my brethren,
my kinsmen, according to the flesh, who are Israelites?
Now we should see the confusion and the doubt.
If you're an Israelite and you're thinking, hold on.
I've got the promise.
I mean, it says everlasting.
Why why are you so heavy and sorrowful for me?
I don't understand what's going on here.
Well, that causes Paul to write Romans 9, verse
6, not as though the word had got to take a nun effect.
If the Israelites are the people of God's mercy unconditionally
and sovereignly elected by God, which we just established they were.
Given all the spiritual privileges from God, which we just established they were.
If so many have rejected Christ, that this Jesus had not saved all of
Israel, has the word of God taken none effect.
In other words, has the word of God failed?
What a question.
Now, Paul writes a profound truth to answer the question.
Notice Paul doesn't just say, no, you dummy.
Because that's what I probably would have said.
But Paul explains this in a way that they cannot argue.
Did you realize Paul is very smart and wise?
Amen?
Would you agree with me on that?
I mean, divinely inspired by the Holy Ghost of the living God?
I mean, listen, he tells exactly what needs to be told.
So we're going to look at this now.
And he answered the question again.
He says again in verse 6, if we continue that verse, for they are not all Israel which are of Israel.
This turns us to look at number two, the plan of mercy.
We've seen the people of mercy, but now we're going to see the plan of mercy, to the Jew reading or listening to this.
They would not have liked what Paul just said.
What do you mean, not all Israelites are not of Israel?
How does that even make sense?
Well, he explains by methodically narrowing down who is truly God's people.
Romans 97 says this, neither because they
are the seed of Abraham, are they all children, but in Isaac, shall thy seed be called?
When God promised a covenant heir to Abraham, it was a promise through Sarah.
The problem was, Sarah was barren.
So she devised a plan for Abraham.
She got impatient and she advised a
plan for Abraham to lie with her handmaid Hagar, which he agreed too foolishly, and through this, a son named Ishmael was born.
Now, did God bless Ishmael?
He did.
But Ishmael did not receive the covenant promise.
How did God bless Ishmael then?
Well, in Genesis 16, verses 8 through 12.
And he said, Hagar, Sarah's maid, whence comest thou?
And whither wilt thou go?
And she said, I flee from the face of my mistress Sarah.
Imagine this.
Imagine Sarah saying, hey, I'm barren.
And so go lay with my handmade and have a child with her.
And then he goes and does that.
And all of a sudden there's a child and there's a little bit of drama in the house.
Could y'all imagine that for any hematics?
Okay, yeah.
So there was some issues.
So Sarah's like, listen, you got to go.
Like, this ain't no good.
I regret what happened here.
And so she flew from the face of her mistress.
And the angel, the Lord said unto her, return to thy mistress and submit thyself unto her hands.
And the angel of the Lord said unto her, I will multiply thy seed exceedingly.
That it shall not be numbered for multitude.
And the angel of the Lord said unto her, behold, thou art with child, and shalt bear
a son, and shalt call his name, Ishmael, because the Lord hath heard thy affliction, and he will be a wild man.
His hand will be against every man and every man's hand against him, and
he shall dwell in the presence of all his brethren.
Ishmael lived up to this prophecy according to Genesis 25,
18, it says they settled from Havilah the sure,
which is east of Egypt as one goes toward Assyria.
And look what it says.
He settled in defiance of all his relatives.
This is Ishmael we're talking about.
Listen, you're going to have to listen quickly.
I know we're going a lot of places very fast.
Now where he's settled,
If you look at, you know, kind of history and geography, we know this as the Arabian Peninsula.
It is the land of the Arab nations, nations such as Bahrain, Kuwait, Omen, Qatar, Saudi Arabia, United Arab Emirates and
Yemen, and also includes small parts of southern Iraq and Jordan.
This area of the world is marked with violence and terrorism.
Listen, there's areas of this area that we could not go safely.
I mean, it is a place of violence.
not all of it, but is a place of exactly what God said it really would be.
It is also interesting that just like Jacob, Ishmael had 12 sons, yet still, with all
this symbolism, he was not the covenant error.
Why?
Genesis 17 makes it clear.
When he goes back and talks to Abraham, then Abraham fell upon
his face and laughed and said in his heart, shall a child be born unto him that is a 100 years old?
Could you imagine a child being born to you at a hundred?
I'm not going to make you raise your hand and say who's the closest to 100 and then ask you, hey, would you like to have a kid?
You know that?
No.
Right?
We can go ahead and say, absolutely not.
That be crazy.
Well, Abraham thought the same thing, so he fell on his face not in reverence, but in laughing.
And shall Sarah, that is 90 years old.
Ladies, could you imagine having a baby at 90?
How come they had a greater response than the men just then?
You notice that?
Absolutely not, right?
And Abraham said unto God, oh, that Ishmael might live before thee, and God said, Sarah, thy wife.
In other words, I don't want to pass that up.
Abraham literally says, hey, I've got Ishmael.
Oh, that he might live before thee.
Because what you're saying is impossible.
Now, we know that Luke said that with God, all things are possible.
Nothing is impossible with him.
Amen.
Y'all with me?
So, and God said, Sarah, thy wife shall bear thee a son indeed.
I kind of wish God would have said, you know what?
Because I said so.
But anyway, and thou shalt call his name Isaac.
And I'll establish my covenant with him for an everlasting.
Everyone say everlasting covenant and with his seed after him.
See, God had a plan.
And that plan was a promise through Isaac.
Now, at this point, any devout or even casual Jew would say yes and amen.
God chose Isaac, not Ishmael.
Of course, there's no arguing that.
As a matter of fact, they would say that in pride.
They would stand up, puff their chest, and we are of Isaac.
Paul continues.
Look at verse eight.
That is, they which are the children of the flesh.
These are not the children of God, but the children of the promise are counted for the seed.
It is not enough to be a child of Abraham.
If that was the case, the Ishmaelites would be under the Abrahamic covenant just like Isaac.
But Isaac was the child of promise, therefore, he was counted for the seed.
So God's chosen people becomes more specific.
We continue to narrow it down through scripture.
Look at verses 9 through 10.
For this is the word of promise.
At this time will I come and Sarah shall have a son, and
not only this, but when Rebecca also had conceived by one, even by our father Isaac.
So here with another example of God's chosen choice,
Abraham and Sarah had Isaac, Isaac had Rebecca.
Isaac and Rebecca sorry, had twins.
Now this is where it gets even more seemingly complicated.
Because think about it.
Okay, we can God chose Abram out of out of the land of Chaldeans.
We can, you know, we don't know why outside of God's
sovereign election, but we can get on board with that.
God chose Abram.
Abram didn't deserve it.
Abrams wasn't seeking here.
God came to Abram and said, get up out of this land and do what I say.
And I bless you.
All right, we can get with that.
Okay, well, Abraham had a covenant air, or promised to him, they got impatient.
So we slept with Hagar.
Hagar had Ishmael and that wasn't the covenant seed, though.
So, God had a miracle work, and now we have Isaac.
So it's easy to think, okay, well, obviously Ishmael can't be a part of it.
So Isaac, that's pretty easy to understand.
The easy to understand part is no longer here, folks.
Let me just tell you.
So, we narrow it down even more.
Look at verses 11 through 13.
This has caused more problems with people than it should.
For the children being not yet born.
talking about the twins in the womb.
Neither having done any good or evil.
that the purpose of God according to the election might stand, not of works, but of him that calleth.
It was said to her, the elder shall serve the younger.
As it is written, Jacob, have I loved, but Esau have I hated.
Again, we can understand that God chose Abraham.
We can understand that being a direct descendant of Abraham is not enough with the example of Ishmael.
That wasn't Sarah's son, that was Hagar's son, but twins in the same womb.
We see yet again God's unconditional election here.
for the children being not yet born yet.
Neither having done any good or evil, that the purpose of God, according
to election, might stand, not of works, but of him, that calleth.
See, this sounds, like God chose one over the other.
It's almost as if we can connect this to Ephesians chapter 2.
For by grace, are you safe through faith and not of yourselves?
It is the gift of God, not of works because any man should boast.
And we sit here and we say, 0 my goodness.
So if God loved Jacob and hated Esau, what does that even mean?
Well, how much clearer can Paul be here?
Verse 12 says it was said unto her, the elder shall serve the younger.
That was out of line with the culture.
See, God has a plan here and he's trying, he's trying to,
what he's really trying to do is he's trying to say, listen, you can have
your plans all you want, but my plan is greater.
So the elder shall serve the younger, and then
you get to one of the most controversial verses all the Bible, as it
is written, Jacob have I loved, but Esau have I hated?
How do we reconcile this?
There's going to be some people that say, oh, there it is.
God chose some to love, and obviously,
if he don't love you, he hates you, so God chose others to hate.
Now, how do we do that in New Testament terms?
God chose some for heaven.
God chose some for hell.
It's called double predetermination.
Now, listen, we're gonna learn, that's not what we're talking about here.
Y'all with me?
That's not what we're talking about here.
How do we reconcile this, though?
We cannot just avoid it, even though it's quite uncomfortable.
By the way, stop avoiding uncomfortable scripture.
You will never grow deeper in your faith if
you just nitpick and or not nitpick, but just kind
of, you know, cherry pick versus that make you feel good.
Wrestle with God's word.
Amen.
There's a couple things we got to understand here.
Right out of the gate.
Let's not forget the truth Paul is exposing.
He is explaining how not all Israelites have accepted Jesus Christ.
He does so by using foolproof examples from Israel's history in the Old Testament.
First, when Paul uses the term love and hate in
regard to Jacob and Esau, he is not speaking in simple terms like we immediately go to.
If that was the case.
Now, hear me out here.
If it was the fact that, hey, I love this person, but I hate despise.
I hate this person, don't want to be with this person, don't want to be around this person.
I hate that person.
If that was the case, then we would
have to hate our father and mother and wife and children.
Y'all with me?
Luke 14, 26, if any man come to me and hate not his father and
mother and wife and children and brethren and sisters, yea,
and his own life also, he cannot be my disciple.
I'm going to be honest with you.
You can look at me all spiritual if you want to.
I'd have a problem with that.
Can't tell me to hate my mama.
Hey, man.
Some of y'all need a love on your mama.
What's wrong, y'all?
By the way, even outside of that, that would break the Fifth Commandment.
oh.
Now we're getting in some weeds here.
See, see, you can't honor your father and mother if you hate them.
You know what?
I should probably repeat that to some people.
You can't honor your father and your mother if you hate them.
oh, reconciliation might need to happen.
That was not in here.
That was free, too, by the way.
en.
It would also directly disobey God's command to love our wives
as Christ loved the church and gave himself forward in Ephesians five.
How could I love Heather in the way that God's called me to according to scripture if I hated her?
It would absolutely contradict and rebel against God's word regarding children.
Psalm 1273, low children are a heritage
of the Lord, and the fruit of the womb is his reward.
So hate them.
That's not what it says.
Matthew 1914.
But Jesus said, suffer little children and forbid them
not to come unto me, for of such is the kingdom of heaven.
Ephesians 6, verse 4.
And ye fathers provoke not your children a wrath, but bring them
up in the nurture and admonition of the Lord.
Church, it obviously cannot mean that God hated Esau in the way that we use the term.
What this is speaking of is a higher choice.
God tells us to choose Jesus higher than anyone anything else in our life.
Here's the thing.
If I choose my wife over Jesus, then I'm just as good as hated her.
Because I cannot love her like I should.
If I choose my family over Jesus, then
I put my family in a level of idolatry before the Lord.
If I choose my own life and ambitions and things that I want, then I am choosing my life as an idol, against the Lord.
Everyone understand it.
We gotta make a higher choice.
That's why in every part of our life, we got to choose
Jesus, higher and greater, than everything and anything else.
And here God is choosing the continuous covenant through Jacob rather than Esau.
But secondly, we have to understand what Romans 9.12 was really referring to.
It was said unto her, the elder shall serve the younger.
In scripture, God uses many examples of breaking the mold of our tradition with who he uses.
Think about people later on in the story like Joseph and David, right?
They were the younger ones.
They weren't the ones that think about David.
Literally, he goes out here and he thinks, hey, we need a king.
And he's like, well, none of these older brothers are it.
So, you know, do you got any more?
Well, we got David.
He's in the field, though.
Why would you want him?
Well, because God chose him.
You know, Joseph, younger, telling his brothers, hey, I had a dream.
You're going to all bow down to me.
They're like, huh, okay, bud, we're going to sell you into slavery.
I mean, that's pretty much how that went down, right?
That's how contrary to the culture it was.
But yet God said, the elder shall serve the younger.
It was to fulfill his plan.
But we don't find in scripture that Esau personally ever serve Jacob.
You won't find it.
Esau, the person, never served Jacob, the person.
But we do see that Edom, or the Edomites
that came from Esau, served Israel, who came from Isaac.
Genesis 361.
Now these are the generations of Esau, who is Edom?
Genesis 36, 8, 9, thus dwelt Esau and Mount Seer, Esau, is Edom.
And these are the generations of Esau, the father of the Edomites in Mount Seer.
Well, what happened under King David's rule?
2 Samuel 8, 14, and he put garrisons in Edom
throughout all Edom, put he garrisons, and all they have Edom, became David's servant.
We see the fulfillment of scripture, and the Lord preserved David whithersoever he went.
Church, this text has nothing to do with the salvation of Jacob or Esau.
But rather the choosing of one nation over the other.
Now, real quick.
We're gonna have to continue this line over the coming up next week.
I told you, we're gonna have to go deep.
What does it have to do with us today?
There's 2 things I want to point out today.
First off,
using the same line of thinking.
In our society, we may not be Israel, but in our society,
what we have thought is, well, I'm on a church roll, I'm good.
Well, well, preacher, I go to church and I
do all the things, so, I've got the new covenant.
I'm saved.
I'm born again.
Why?
Well, because I do all the things that say people do.
If we take the same example,
that Paul uses from Israel and apply it to today, understand something.
You can be here all day long.
And not be a child of God.
So I bring that up not to confuse you, but to warn you, we do not put our faith and trust in things or attendance or participation.
We put our faith and trust in Jesus.
But also, maybe you're here today.
And I want to point out a scripture.
It's not going to be up there, so don't worry about it.
But when he asked and when he clarified,
Not as though the word of God had taken that effect, remember how he said something that was contrary to what they would think?
So, Has God's word failed?
I don't know about you, but There's been times in my life.
Well, I know the promises of God.
I know what God said about it.
As a matter of fact, I read it over and over again, right?
When I get anxious, I read Philippians 4.
When I, you know, when I get discouraged, I'll read some of the psalms.
Like, I mean, there's things that I read, but it doesn't seem to immediately just get me back where I need to be.
I don't know about you and I don't I don't mean to be irreverent here at all, but sometimes I thank God is...
What's going on here?
God, I need out of this.
You said, God, you said you never leave me nor forsake
me, Lord, but I don't, I don't feel you right now.
Okay, God, I know you said the fiery trials.
But I'm not getting strength, and I'm getting weakened.
And we may never say it out loud, we think, as God's word failed us.
What happens when you believe God's word, yet nothing ever seems to work out?
What happens when you know the promises and oracles of God, yet they never seem to happen in your life?
Everybody else seems to see life seems to do that.
By the way, I want you to know something real quick.
If you're here and you think that you're all alone in your struggle.
I can guarantee you as someone that people go to to talk, right?
And, hey, listen, it's confidential and you can believe that.
I just want to encourage you.
You are not alone.
We all struggle, and we all suffer.
And if we could just get out of our pride, we might be able to help each other more.
But see, it's easy to judge the doubter that asks, has the word of God failed?
But have we not wished for that to ourselves in time of trouble?
God, you said you supply my every need, but I mean, we're not going to make it this month.
God, you said that you would heal me, but yet, why am I still sick?
Church, the answer for us the same for Israel.
Trust God's plan.
When your life begins to fall apart.
Trust his plan.
When your marriage begins to falter.
Trust God's plan.
When your children begin to stray and go every which way, Trust God's plan.
When your friends abandon you.
Trust God's plan.
When your health betrays you.
His word and his will.
is sure and perfect.
You realize that if we could see it through the other side.
If we could see the end of that trial.
If God could just say, okay, here's what I'm going to do in your life, and
here's the starting point and the finish point.
So you see, you can trust me because I'm showing you that it's going to be okay.
There's no trust in that.
That's why God doesn't do it.
This morning, may I remind you of the words of King David who knew something about the ups and downs in life.
Psalm 374 through 6 says, delight yourself in the Lord.
And he will give you the desires of your heart.
Commit your way to the Lord, trust also in him, and he will do it.
He will bring forth your righteousness as the light and your judgment as the noonday.
Trust in the Lord.